[{"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The resolution of an <i>n</i> bit DAC with a maximum input of 5 V is 5 mV. The value of <i>n</i> is</div>", "options": ["8", "9", "10", "11"], "answer": "Option C", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106001", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q1_explanation_1(image)1000 = 5 or N = 10.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5770#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">2's complement of binary number 0101 is</div>", "options": ["1011", "1111", "1101", "1110"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106001", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>1's complement of 0101 is 1010 and 2's complement is 1010+1 = 1011.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5394#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">An OR gate has 4 inputs. One input is high and the other three are low. The output</div>", "options": ["is low", "is high", "is alternately high and low", "may be high or low depending on relative magnitude of inputs"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106001", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>In OR any input high means high output.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5571#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">Decimal number 10 is equal to binary number</div>", "options": ["1110", "1010", "1001", "1000"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106001", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>1010 = 8 + 2 = 10 in decimal.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5384#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">Both OR and AND gates can have only two inputs.</div>", "options": ["True", "False"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106001", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Any number of inputs are possible.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-6487#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A device which converts BCD to seven segment is called</div>", "options": ["encoder", "decoder", "multiplexer", "none of these"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106002", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Decoder converts binary/BCD to alphanumeric.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5494#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">In 2's complement representation the number 11100101 represents the decimal number</div>", "options": ["+37", "-31", "+27", "-27"], "answer": "Option D", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106002", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>A = 11100101. Therefore <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> = 00011010 and A' = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> + 1 = 00011011 = 16 + 8 + 2 + 1 = 27. Therefore A = -27.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5565#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A decade counter skips</div>", "options": ["binary states 1000 to 1111", "binary states 0000 to 0011", "binary states 1010 to 1111", "binary states 1111 to higher"], "answer": "Option C", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106002", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>A decade counter counts from 0 to 9. It has 4 flip-flops. The states skipped are 10 to 15 or 1010 to 1111.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5520#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">BCD input 1000 is fed to a 7 segment display through a BCD to 7 segment decoder/driver. The segments which will lit up are</div>", "options": ["<i>a, b, d</i>", "<i>a, b, c</i>", "all", "<i>a, b, g, c, d</i>"], "answer": "Option C", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106002", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>1000 equals decimal 8 Therefore all segments will lit up.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5493#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A ring counter with 5 flip flops will have</div>", "options": ["5 states", "10 states", "32 states", "infinite states"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106002", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\r\n                                                    No answer description is available. <a class=\"text-link\" href=\"https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5787#comments\"> Let's discuss.</a>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5787#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">For the gate in the given figure the output will be<br/>(image)q11_after_1(image)</div>", "options": ["0", "1", "A", "<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span>"], "answer": "Option D", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106003", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>If A = 0, Y = 1 and A = 1, Y = 0 Therefore Y = <i><span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span></i>.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5807#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">In the expression A + BC, the total number of minterms will be</div>", "options": ["2", "3", "4", "5"], "answer": "Option D", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106003", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>The min terms are <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span>BC + ABC + A<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + A<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>C + AB<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span>.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5456#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The circuit in the given figure is<br/>(image)q13_after_1(image)</div>", "options": ["positive logic XOR gate", "negative logic OR gate", "negative logic AND gate", "positive logic AND gate"], "answer": "Option C", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106003", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Since V(I) is lower state than V(0) it is a negative logic circuit. Since diodes are in <b>reversed</b> parallel, it is an AND gate.</p>\n<p> Note: In Boolean algebra it is recognized that a positive logic OR is a negative logic AND. Similarly a positive logic AND is a negative logic OR.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5725#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">Which of the following is non-saturating?</div>", "options": ["TTL", "CMOS", "ECL", "Both (a) and (b)"], "answer": "Option C", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106003", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Since it is non-saturating, ECL has low propagation delay.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5655#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The number of digits in octal system is</div>", "options": ["8", "7", "9", "10"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106003", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>The octal system has 8 digits 0 to 7.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5361#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The access time of a word in 4 MB main memory is 100 ms. The access time of a word in a 32 kb data cache memory is 10 ns. The average data cache bit ratio is 0.95. The efficiency of memory access time is</div>", "options": ["9.5 ns", "14.5 ns", "20 ns", "95 ns"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106004", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Access time = 0.95 x 10 + 0.05 x 100.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5962#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The expression Y = <span class=\"symbol\">p</span>M (0, 1, 3, 4) is</div>", "options": ["POS", "SOP", "Hybrid", "none of the above"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106004", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>This is product of sums expression.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5460#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">An 8 bit DAC has a full scale output of 2 mA and full scale error of \u00b1 0.5%. If input is 10000000 the range of outputs is</div>", "options": ["994 to 1014 \u03bcA", "990 to 1020 \u03bcA", "800 to 1200 \u03bcA", "none of the above"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106004", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>10000000 = 128, 11111111 = 255 </p>\n<p>If there is no error, output = (image)q18_explanation_1(image) = 1004\u03bcA. </p>\n<p>Maximum error = (image)q18_explanation_2(image) </p>\n<p>Hence range of output 994 to 1014 \u03bcA.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5843#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">Decimal 43 in hexadecimal and BCD number system is respectively.</div>", "options": ["B2, 01000011", "2B, 01000011", "2B, 00110100", "B2, 01000100"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106004", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(43)<sub>10</sub> = (2B)<sub>16</sub></p>\n<p>(43)<sub>10</sub> = (01000011)<sub>2</sub> .</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5945#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The circuit of the given figure realizes the function<br/>(image)q20_after_1(image)</div>", "options": ["Y = (<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>) C + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">DE</span>", "Y = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">D</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">E</span>", "AB + C +DE", "AB + C(D + E)"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106004", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q20_explanation_1(image) or </p>\n<p>Y = (<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>)C + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">DE</span>.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5750#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">An AND gate has two inputs A and B and one inhibit input 3, Output is 1 if</div>", "options": ["A = 1, B = 1, S = 1", "A = 1, B = 1, S = 0", "A = 1, B = 0, S = 1", "A = 1, B = 0, S = 0"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106005", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>All AND inputs must be 1 and inhibit 0 for output to be 1.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5434#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The greatest negative number which can be stored is 8 bit computer using 2's complement arithmetic is</div>", "options": ["- 256", "- 128", "- 255", "- 127"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106005", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>The largest negative number is 1000 0000 = -128.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5704#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A JK flip flop has <i>t<sub>pd</sub></i>= 12 ns. The largest modulus of a ripple counter using these flip flops and operating at 10 MHz is</div>", "options": ["16", "64", "128", "256"], "answer": "Option D", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106005", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Number of flip-flops = (image)q23_explanation_1(image) = 8.333 say 8 </p>\n<p>Modulus = 2<sup>8</sup> = 256.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5838#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The basic storage element in a digital system is</div>", "options": ["flip flop", "counter", "multiplexer", "encoder"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106005", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Storing can be done only in memory and flip-flop is a memory element.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5528#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">In a ripple counter,</div>", "options": ["whenever a flip flop sets to 1, the next higher FF toggles", "whenever a flip flop sets to 0, the next higher FF remains unchanged", "whenever a flip flop sets to 1, the next higher FF faces race condition", "whenever a flip flop sets to 0, the next higher FF faces race condition"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106005", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>In a ripple counter the effect ripples through the counter.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5518#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A 12 bit ADC is used to convert analog voltage of 0 to 10 V into digital. The resolution is</div>", "options": ["2.44 mV", "24.4 mV", "1.2 V", "none of the above"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106006", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q26_explanation_1(image).</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5761#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">For the truth table of the given figure Y =<br/>(image)q27_after_1(image)</div>", "options": ["A + B + C", "<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> + BC", "<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span>", "<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>"], "answer": "Option D", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106006", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Y = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> C + A<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + A <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> C = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> (<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + C) + A <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> (<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + C) = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> + A<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>(A + A) = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5739#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A full adder can be made out of</div>", "options": ["two half adders", "two half adders and a OR gate", "two half adders and a NOT gate", "three half adders"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106006", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q28_explanation_1(image)</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5758#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">If the functions <i>w, x, y, z</i> are as follows.<br/><i>w</i> = R + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">P</span>Q + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">R</span>S , <br/><i>x</i> = PQ<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">R</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">S</span> + PQ<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">R</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">S</span> + P<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">Q</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">R</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">S</span><br/>(image)q29_after_1(image)<br/>(image)q29_after_2(image)<br/>Then</div>", "options": ["<i>w = z x = z</i>", "<i>w = z, x = y</i>", "<i>w = y</i>", "<i>w = y = z</i>"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106006", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Use k-map, then it will be easy.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5936#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The output of a half adder is</div>", "options": ["SUM", "CARRY", "SUM and CARRY", "none of the above"], "answer": "Option C", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106006", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q30_explanation_1(image)</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5586#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">Minimum number of 2-input NAND gates required to implement the function F = (<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">x</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">y</span>) (Z + W) is</div>", "options": ["3", "4", "5", "6"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106007", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p><i>F</i> = (<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">x</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">y</span>) (z + w) = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">xy</span>.(z + w)</p>\n<p>= <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">xy</span>z + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">xy</span>w</p>\n<p>= (image)q31_explanation_1(image) minimum no. of 2 input NAND gate.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5872#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">Which device has one input and many outputs?</div>", "options": ["Multiplexer", "Demultiplexer", "Counter", "Flip flop"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106007", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Demultiplexer takes data from one line and directs it to any of its N output depending on the status of its select lines.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5504#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A carry look ahead adder is frequently used for addition because</div>", "options": ["it costs less", "it is faster", "it is more accurate", "is uses fewer gates"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106007", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>In look ahead carry adder the carry is directly derived from the gates when original inputs are being added. Hence the addition is fast. This process requires more gates and is costly.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5703#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The counter in the given figure is<br/>(image)q34_after_1(image)</div>", "options": ["Mod 3", "Mod 6", "Mod 8", "Mod 7"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106007", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>When counter is 110 the counter resets. Hence mod 6.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5833#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">In register index addressing mode the effective address is given by</div>", "options": ["index register value", "sum of the index register value and the operand", "operand", "difference of the index register value and the operand"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106007", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>4 = 2<sup>2</sup>, in up scaling digit will be shifted by two bit in right direction.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5875#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">7BF<sub>16</sub> = __________ <sub>2</sub></div>", "options": ["0111 1011 1110", "0111 1011 1111", "0111 1011 0111", "0111 1011 0011"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106008", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>7BF<sub>16</sub> = 7 x 16<sup>2</sup> + 11 x 16<sup>1</sup> + 15 x 16<sup>0</sup> = 1983 in decimal = 0111 1011 1111 in binary.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5405#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">For the minterm designation Y = \u2211 m (1, 3, 5, 7) the complete expression is</div>", "options": ["Y = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>C + A <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> C", "Y = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> C + A <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> C + ABC + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> BC", "Y = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> C + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span>BC + A <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>C", "Y = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + ABC + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>C + A <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>C"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106008", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Decimal number 1 = binary number 001 = <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>C Decimal number 7 = binary number 111= ABC, Decimal number 3 = binary number 011= <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span>BC Decimal number 5 = binary number 101= A<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>C . Hence result.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5458#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">Zero suppression is not used in actual practice.</div>", "options": ["True", "False"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106008", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Zero suppression is commonly used.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-6506#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A counter type A/D converter contains a 4 bit binary ladder and a counter driven by a 2 MHz clock. Then conversion time</div>", "options": ["8 \u03bc sec", "10 \u03bc sec", "2 \u03bc sec", "5 \u03bc sec"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106008", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q39_explanation_1(image)</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5912#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The hexadecimal number (3E8)<sub>16</sub> is equal to decimal number</div>", "options": ["1000", "982", "768", "323"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106008", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>3 x 16<sup>2</sup> + 14 x 16<sup>1</sup> + 8 = 1000.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5762#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The number of distinct Boolean expression of 4 variables is</div>", "options": ["16", "256", "1024", "65536"], "answer": "Option D", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106009", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>2<sup>2<sup>n</sup></sup> = 2<sup>2<sup>4</sup></sup> = 2<sup>16</sup> .</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5930#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">The fixed count that should be used so that the output register will represent the input for a 6 bit dual slope A/D converter uses a reference of -6v and a 1 MHz clock. It uses a fixed count of 40 (101000).</div>", "options": ["000110", "0010", "1111", "011101"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106009", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>If (image)q42_explanation_1(image) is made to be unity, the O/P count N<sub>2</sub> = <i>e<sub>i</sub>, </i> N<sub>1</sub> = 6 = 000110.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5911#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">For the K map in the given figure the simplified Boolean expression is<br/>(image)q43_after_1(image)</div>", "options": ["<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">D</span> + ABC", "<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> C + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">D</span> + ABC", "<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> C + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">D</span> + ACD", "<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span> + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">A</span> <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">D</span> + AB <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">C</span>"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106009", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q43_explanation_1(image)</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5727#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A memory system of size 16 k bytes is to be designed using memory chips which have 12 address lines and 4 data lines each. The number of such chips required to design the memory system is</div>", "options": ["2", "4", "8", "18"], "answer": "Option C", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106009", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q44_explanation_1(image).</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5803#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">In a 7 segment display, LEDs <i>b</i> and <i>c</i> lit up. The decimal number displayed is</div>", "options": ["9", "7", "3", "1"], "answer": "Option D", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106009", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>(image)q45_explanation_1(image)</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5492#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">AB + A<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> =</div>", "options": ["B", "A", "1", "0"], "answer": "Option B", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106010", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>AB + A<span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span> = A(B + <span style=\"text-decoration:overline;\">B</span>) = A . 1 = A.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5461#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">In a BCD to 7 segment decoder the minimum and maximum number of outputs active at any time is</div>", "options": ["2 and 7", "3 and 7", "1 and 6", "3 and 6"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106010", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Minimum number of outputs when input is decimal 1 and maximum number of outputs when input is decimal 8.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5678#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">A three state switch has three outputs. These are</div>", "options": ["low, low and high", "low, high, high", "low. floating, low", "low, high, floating"], "answer": "Option D", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106010", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Third state is floating.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5603#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">Maxterm designation for A + B + C is</div>", "options": ["M<sub>0</sub>", "M<sub>1</sub>", "M<sub>3</sub>", "M<sub>4</sub>"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106010", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>A + B + C = 000 = M<sub>0</sub> .</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5645#comments"}, {"question": "<div class=\"bix-td-qtxt table-responsive w-100\">1's complement of 11100110 is</div>", "options": ["00011001", "10000001", "00011010", "00000000"], "answer": "Option A", "url": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/106010", "explanation": "<div class=\"bix-ans-description table-responsive\">\n<p>Replace 1 by 0 and 0 by 1.</p>\n</div>", "discussion_link": "https://www.indiabix.com/electronics-and-communication-engineering/digital-electronics/discussion-5393#comments"}]